<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Forma sive descriptio convocationis celebrandæ prout ab antiquo observari consuevit.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Convocation.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700-1701</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4184A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC N4148</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895200</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895200</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152633</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79688)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152633)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2310:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Forma sive descriptio convocationis celebrandæ prout ab antiquo observari consuevit.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Convocation.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>between 1700 and 1701?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Latin text is attributed by the commentator to Matthew Parker, Archbishop of Canterbury.</note>
                  <note>The author of the English commentary is unidentified.</note>
                  <note>The text contains references to the 2nd edition of Francis Atterbury's "Rights, powers, and privileges of an English convocation" and to White Kennett's "Occasional letter," both dated 1701.</note>
                  <note>Drop-head title.</note>
                  <note>The words "Forma" and "antiquo" are followed by superscript 1 and 2 respectively, referring to footnotes.</note>
                  <note>Dated 1700 by Wing, 1701? by ESTC.</note>
                  <note>Text in two columns.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles, California.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152633:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>FORMA<note n="1" place="bottom">This <hi>Formulary</hi> of holding a Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as by ancient Cuſtom it <hi>uſed</hi> to be Held, is unhappily Call'd by Dr. <hi>Atterbury</hi> in the Firſt Edition of his <hi>Rights, Powers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 376. <hi>A Directory of Archbiſhop</hi> CRANMER's: When it was certainly drawn up by Archbiſhop <hi>Parker</hi> (as ſoon after confeſt by Dr. <hi>A.</hi>) from all the Precedents before and at the <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> for a <hi>Rule</hi> to Himſelf in Opening his firſt Convocation, <hi>Jan.</hi> 12. 1562. and for a ſtanding <hi>Pattern</hi> to his Succeſſors.</note> SIVE DESCRIPTIO Convocationis Celebrandae, <hi>Prout ab Antiquo</hi>
                  <note n="2" place="bottom">Dr. <hi>Atterbury</hi> has advanc'd a Pernicious as well as a Miſtaken Scheme, that the <hi>Act of Submiſſion</hi> entirely altred the Method and the very Nature of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Convocations; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Summon'd by the Archbiſhop, Govern'd, Prorogu'd and Diſſolv'd by Him: but ſince entirely <hi>Subject</hi> to the King; and the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>now</hi> made a <hi>Miniſterial Officer,</hi> and a <hi>pure Inſtrument</hi> of the Crown. If our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation had been built on this fatal <hi>Eraſtian</hi> Principle; The <hi>Form</hi> of holding Convocations muſt have needs altred with the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of 'em. But as really there was no other change in the Nature of our Synods, but only as the Archbiſhops were reſtrain'd from Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling 'em without the King's Licenſe and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: So this little Change did not at all affect the manner of their Sitting and Acting under the Government and Preſidency of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan. And therefore this Solemn <hi>Form</hi> do's no where drop and old Cuſtom, or advance a new Practiſe, or adapt any thing to the Act of Submiſſion; but refers All to antecedent Uſage and long Preſcription— <hi>Prout ab Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo— conſuevit.— Ex More — Ex laudabili &amp; antiqua Ordinatione.—Solet obſervari,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>obſervari conſuevit.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SCiendum eſt quod Omnes qui Autoritate<note n="3" place="bottom">It was a late Artifice of Dr. <hi>A.</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt the lower Clergy from the Juriſdiction of Archbiſhop and Biſhops in Convocation, by pretending, <hi>first,</hi> they were cited by the King in his <hi>Parliamentary Writs;</hi> and at <hi>last,</hi> by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting, That the <hi>Provincial Writ</hi> was a like immediate Summons by the King, which the Archbiſhop barely executes as a <hi>proper Officer;</hi> his ſhare in convening his Clergy, being no longer <hi>Authoritative,</hi> but purely <hi>Miniſterial.</hi> Which yet does not only ſtrike at the very <hi>Being</hi> of a Church, but directly contradicts this <hi>Form;</hi> where All the Clergy are expreſly ſaid to be <hi>Cited by the Authority</hi> of the Moſt Reverend the Archbiſhop, to Appear before <hi>Him.</hi>
                  </note> Reverendiſſimi Domini Archiepiſcopi <hi>Cantuar'</hi> citantur ad comparendum coram Eo in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Capitulari Eccleſiae Cathedralis Divi <hi>Pauli London'</hi> duodecimo die <hi>Januar'</hi> prox' tenentur praefixo tempore intereſſe, atque in eâdem Eccleſiâ Cath' praeſtolari Adventum dicti Reverendiſſimi. Qui ex More
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152633:2"/>paulo post octavam ante Meridiem illius diei ſolet cum celebri Comitatu apu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Portum Thamiſis vocatum <hi>Paul's Wharf</hi> in terram deſcendere, atque ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde Praeeuntibus Advocatis &amp; Procuratoribus Curiae <hi>Cantuar'</hi> certiſque Reverendiſſimi Generoſis ac Virgifero Convocationis, ad Eccleſiam Cath' Divi Pauli London recta tendere, atque in chorum ibidem ingredi. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi poſtquam in ſtallo Decani collocatus fuerit, ac preces dixerit, tam Ipſe quam Reliqui Epiſcopi Praeſentes habitu Convocationis togati ex atroque Chori la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere in ſuis Stallis ſeſe conſtituunt &amp; mox incipiunt Preces<note n="4" place="bottom">The Service and Sacrifice of the Maſs, was reform'd into purer <hi>Latin</hi> Prayers, and a right Communion of the Bleſſed Sacrament. For the uſe of the Synod, there was drawn up by the Archbiſhop only, and by him alone pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, <hi>Forma Precum in utraque Domo Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationis,</hi> &amp;c. And according to this Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the Archbiſhop at the Head of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, this Ancient Form has receiv'd ſome Alterations and Additions, with new occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Hymns and Collects, at the diſcretion of our ſucceſſive Archbiſhops, without any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Conſent, or active concern of the Lower Clergy, who herein ſubmitted to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Authority of the Archbiſhop; who is preſum'd indeed not to act in theſe Matters, without Counſel and Conſent of his <hi>Suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans.</hi>
                  </note>, quibus Spiritus Sancti gratia invocatur, ac Communio ſubſequitur. Ac tempore Offertorii tam dictus Reverendiſſimus quam coeteri Suffraganei Epiſcopi rem divinam celebranti ordine progredientes Oblationem offerre ex more debent. Peractâ in hunc morem Re Divina, ſolet doctus Aliquis ex Caetu Convocationis ſive Superioris ſive Inferioris Domus ad hoc ſelectus è Suggeſtu in medio Chori Concionem<note n="5" place="bottom">As the Archbiſhop in the Rubrick of the <hi>Form of Prayers for Convocation,</hi> has directed, That they ſhall be Read in the Upper Houſe, by the <hi>Junior</hi> Biſhop; and in the Lower Houſe, by the <hi>Prolocutor:</hi> So the ordering of the Sermon, and appointing a Preacher, has been alway leſt to the Archbiſhop's <hi>Sole</hi> Power; who aſſigns the Office to any <hi>One</hi> of his Suffragans, or any <hi>Other</hi> of his Inferiour Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, as he thinks moſt Fit and Proper.</note> ad Clerum ibidem congregatum Latine proferre: Quâ abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ, Reverendiſſimus ſtatim ſe confert in Domum Capitularem dictae Eccleſiae; ſequentibus Epiſcopis &amp; toto Clero. Quibus ingreſſis ac ſecluſis Extraneis, Reverendiſſimo ac caeteris ſuis Co-Epiſcopis in ſuis ſedibus ordine conſidenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ac reliquo Clero<note n="6" place="bottom">It much explains the true nature of our Provincial Synods to obſerve, That the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop is alway repreſented, <hi>Pro tribunali ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens;</hi> and ſometimes <hi>in throno ſuo collocatus.</hi> The Biſhops are deſcrib'd to be <hi>Ordine confiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> and <hi>Secum</hi> (i. e. <hi>cum Archiepiſcopo</hi>) <hi>Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes.</hi> But the Prolocutor and Lower Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy are evermore found in the Upper Houſe, or Preſence of the Archbiſhop and Biſhops, to be <hi>Stantes</hi> and <hi>Circumſtantes.</hi> Dr. <hi>A.</hi> indeed would make this Decency to be an Innovation: For he deſcribes the old Provincial Synods, to have Presbyters alway <hi>Sitting with</hi> the Biſhops, and the Deacons and People only <hi>ſtanding.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rights, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> Yet as this was not the Figure of <hi>Provincial,</hi> but of <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan</hi> Synods only, where the Prieſts were, and ſtill are <hi>Co-Aſſeſſors</hi> with their Biſhop: So he does not in any part of his Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings offer one Inſtance, where the <hi>Sitting</hi> of Presbyters in preſence of the Biſhops, was ever Allow'd in any one <hi>Engliſh Provincial</hi> Synod.</note> circumſtante, Reverendus Dominus Epiſcopus <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152633:2"/>Mandatum<note n="7" place="bottom">It is a ſhameful Aſſertion of the Author of <hi>the Power of the Lower-Houſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. that theſe Certificates or <hi>Returns</hi> to the Archbiſhop are <hi>All made in Virtue of the King's Writ of Summons, which they do or ſhould Recite; not at all in Virtue of the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's Mandate any further than it</hi> Executes <hi>this Writ.</hi> When in truth all the Returns from the Dean of the Province and from the other Suffragans regularly made, either do not recite the <hi>King's Writ,</hi> becauſe they execute only the <hi>Archbiſhop's Mandate:</hi> Or when they do recite the <hi>King's Writ,</hi> it is only as they find it included in the <hi>Mandate,</hi> and ſo recite it as a <hi>Part</hi> of that Mandate. But it is not at all in Virtue of the King's Writ, that the Dean Cites the Suffragans, or thoſe Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragans cite their Clergy, no ſuch <hi>Civil</hi> Call; but a pure <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Summons, and a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical</hi> Execution of the Archbiſhop's Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datory Letters. Therefore at the Opening of a Convocation, the Archbiſhop does of late Order the King's Writ to be ſolemnly read, to juſtifie his Calling and Holding of it by Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the King's Licenſe and Command di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to him. Yet the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> does not here at all refer himſelf to the Royal Writ, but Purely to the Archiepiſcopal <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date,</hi> which alone he here introduces, and of which alone he certifies the Execution; with no manner of <hi>Return</hi> to the King, nor of immediate <hi>Reſpect</hi> to any Royal Writ. <hi>Mandatum ſibi a dicto Reverendiſſimo — introducere tenetur — cum debito Certificatorio ſuper Executione ejuſdem,</hi> i. e. <hi>Mandati.</hi>
                  </note> ſibi à dicto Reverendiſſimo ad Convocationem hujuſmodi ſubeundam [ſubmonendam] aliàs directum una cum debito Certificatorio ſuper executione ejuſdem introducere, ac debita cum Reverentia eidem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verendiſſimo Patri preſentare &amp; tradere tenetur. Quo quidem Certificatorio perlecto, ſtatim porrigitur eidem Reverendiſſimo Schedula deſcripta, per quam pronuntiat omnes ad eoſdem horam &amp; locum non comparentes<note n="8" place="bottom">To diſturb our Convocations, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the very Being of 'em, Dr. <hi>A.</hi> has ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd a Notion, that the Members are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for their Abſence to the Houſe, and not to the Preſident. When yet by the King's Writ, the Biſhops and Clergy muſt meet <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Archbiſhop,</hi> and muſt therefore an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for their <hi>Non Appearance</hi> to him before whom they ought to Appear. Such <hi>Non Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance</hi> at firſt, or afterward <hi>withdrawing</hi> without His Graces leave, was reputed a Contumacy or obſtinate Contempt of his Graces Authority; for which a Canonical Puniſhment or Cenſure was due; of which kind of Cenſure, and the time of inflicting it the Archbiſhop was the proper Judge, and therefore reſerv'd it to himſelf, and all the Circumſtances of it to his own Pleaſure.</note> contumaces, reſervando poenam eorum contumaciae in aliquem diem competentem pro Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placito ipſius Reverendiſſimi. Praemiſſis ſic expeditis dictus Reverendiſſimus ad Epiſcopos &amp; Clerum tunc Praeſentes Anglice ſive Latine cauſam ſui Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventus ac dictae Convocationis Inchoatae<note n="9" place="bottom">Another fancy of Independence has been rais'd, that at the Opening of every Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Lower Clergy ought <hi>to be put into a capacity of doing Buſineſs,</hi> and may then chuſe their own Buſineſs, and agree upon De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, and even come to Reſolutions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any preceding Advice or Directions from the Preſident and Biſhops. But this Liberty was never till <hi>now</hi> Aſſum'd. The Lower Clergy never thought themſelves ſuch abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Judges in Synodical Affairs, as to make the <hi>first</hi> Steps in them. They waited the Motion of the Archbiſhop and Biſhops, and and were content to follow the Hints and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions given by their Superiours: This did eſtabliſh a Cuſtom for the Archbiſhop to open the Synod in a Speech, that ſhould ſet forth the Cauſes of his Coming there to meet his Brethren and the Reſt of the Clergy; and the Reaſon of thus forming themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Synodical Aſſembly: <hi>Cauſam ſui Adventus ac dictoe Convocationis inchoatoe exponit.</hi>
                  </note> exponit: Quodque ex lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152633:3"/>&amp; antiqua Ordinatione eadem Convocatio in duo<note n="10" place="bottom">Another daring Notion has been rais'd, that the Lower Houſe is a diſtinct Body from the Upper, Separate upon Eſſential Rights of it's <hi>own Body,</hi> with all the Powers and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges of a Houſe, in the Parliamentary ſenſe of the word <hi>Houſe.</hi> But yet <hi>here</hi> the ſame <hi>Body</hi> the Convocation is divided into two <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> the Upper and Lower Houſe, which <hi>Members</hi> have the ſame common <hi>Head</hi> of the whole Body the Archbiſhop. Tho' the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>the Power of the Lower Houſe</hi> has moſt injuriouſly degraded the Archbiſhop into a <hi>Chair-Man or</hi> Moderator <hi>of the Whole Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, when the two Houſes are together;</hi> or when the Upper Houſe is <hi>by it ſelf,</hi> then the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop muſt not be <hi>Preſident</hi> (tho it be his title in the very <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi>) but a <hi>chief Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> at moſt, or the <hi>proper Perſon to Intimate or Notifie</hi> the Act of the Biſhops, p. 15. c. 2. p. 18. c. 1. while the Prolocutor is made by much the greater Man, <hi>Nothing ſingular in the Notion of repreſenting the Prolocutor as Head <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>reſident or Governour of the Lower Houſe.</hi> p. 9. c. 2.</note> Membra divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, nempe in Superiorem atque Inferiorem domum. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde Reverendiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus &amp; caeteri Co-Epiſcopi Superiorem Domum efficiunt; Inferior vero Domus ex Decanis Eccleſiarum Cath' Archidiaconis Collegiorum Magiſtris &amp; Capitulorum Cath' Eccleſiarum necnon Cleri cujuſcunque Dioceſeos Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatoribus conſtat.</p>
               <p>Et quoniam ſi in rerum tractandarum ſerie <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nuſquiſque ex inferiore Domo ſuam ipſe ſententiam quoties viſum eſſet diceret, aut ſi omnes aut plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſimul loquerentur, pareret confuſionem. Igitur ſemper hactenus obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatum fuit, ut <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus aliquis doctus &amp; diſertus ex gremio dictae inferioris Domus in eorum omnium locum ad hoc munus aſſumatur<note n="11" place="bottom">Agreeable to this wild Notion of Houſes <hi>Co-ordinate,</hi> and a Prolocutor <hi>Supreme:</hi> It has been ſuggeſted, that the Lower Clergy by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent right haue always had a Prolocutor as an Original <hi>Preſident</hi> over them. But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly there was a time when A. B. Biſhops and Clergy made but one Houſe; when the Lower Clergy had no right to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from the Biſhops, but by Order or Leave of the Preſident. So withdrawing and debating of a matter referr'd to them; they were but a Select Company or Committe of the Archbiſhops Appointment, and ſome One was taken as a Chairman to manage their ſeparate Debates, and report their Senſe to the Archbiſhop and his Brethren. When the Lower Clergy were by Degrees form'd into a more ſettled State of ſeparation from their Lordſhips, the Archbiſhop allowed them a diſtinct Apartment, which ſoon came to be their <hi>Locus ſolitus,</hi> and a fixt Prolocutor to be choſe at the Beginning, and continue to the End of every Convocation or Synod. But this Miniſterial Officer in the Lower Houſe did by no means exempt the Clergy from their Canonical Subjection to the Archbiſhop, who had hereby a larger exerciſe of Juriſdiction. For he now prevented Confuſion in the Lower Houſe by his preſcribing this Method of Peace and Order: He aſſerted his own Authority, by not ſuffering them to chuſe without his Leave and Admonition: He took care that the Elect ſhould be preſented to him for his Conſent and Approbation: And when Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the Office he muſt be ſubſervient to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Archbiſhop and the whole Synod, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elating the conſent of his Fellow Members <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the moſt Reverend, whenever he ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>required</hi> if both Houſes were together, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r whenever he ſhould be <hi>ſent for</hi> if the Lower Houſe were in a ſeparate Place.</note>; ut Is intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectis
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152633:3"/>&amp; ſcrutatis caeterorum Omnium votis, tanquam unum Eorum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Os &amp; Organum loquatur, &amp; conſonam eorum ſententiam eidem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verendiſſimo, cum ad hoc rogatus ſeu miſſus fuerit, caeteris ſilentibus fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter<note n="12" place="bottom">The Office of Prolocutor and very Name of <hi>Referendary</hi> is from his being the common <hi>Mouth</hi> and <hi>Organ</hi> of the Lower Clergy, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onvey and <hi>relate</hi> their joint Requeſts and Reſolutions to the moſt Reverend; and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y back his Graces Anſwers and further Orders, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s the only Meſſenger of Correſpondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ween the two Houſes. This part of the Conſtitution they would have lately broke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrough, and would have ſent choſen Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers without the Prolocutor to relate the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nſe of the Clergy to the Archbiſhop and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Biſhops. A Violence that for ought ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ears, was never Attempted but in one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>odern Convocation, and even then it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ublickly declared to be againſt the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent of the Preſident and Biſhops, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ainſt the Authority of their Records.</note> referat': Qui ex hoc munere Referendarius ſive Prolocutor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muniter denominatur. Cujus eligendi libera facultas ſemper penes dictam Inferiorem Domum remanet.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde ipſe Reverendiſſimus ſolet eoſdem ex inferiori Domo monere &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hortari, ut ſtatim ſe conferant in dictam Inferiorem Domum<note n="13" place="bottom">'Tis obſervable, that tho' the Body of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Synod ſoon divides into two Members, an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pper and Lower Houſe: Yet the Place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>here the Archbiſhop and Biſhops aſſemble, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> always the <hi>Place of the Synod;</hi> which whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>od of the Prelates and Clergy of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nce is Prorogued <hi>in hunc locum, i. e.</hi> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>om where the Archbiſhop is then ſitting <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>o Tribunali,</hi> and his Suffragans as Co-Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſors with him. And as at the opening of the Synod, the Lower Clergy attended the Preſident in the very ſame Place with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; So at the beginning of every Seſſion, they are preſum'd to pay the ſame Attendance <hi>coram Archiepiſcopo,</hi> in the ſame Place to which they as well as the Biſhops were <hi>Continued</hi> and <hi>Prorogued,</hi> though to ſave unneceſſary trouble the Preſident does commonly accept the Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Prolocutor and two or three Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Members as equivalent to the whole Houſe; and may often excuſe even <hi>their</hi> Abſence, if it be not in Contempt or affected Separation. 'Tis further obſervable, that while the Lower Clergy are ſo attending the Archbiſhop and Biſhops, they are never found to be at their own will, but at the Preſidents Monition: He diſmiſſes them from the Common Place of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, with Leave to retire to their own Apartment.</note>, ibique de viro docto pio &amp; fideli in Prolocutorem ſuum aſſumendo conſultantes, unanimiter conſentiant &amp; eligant, ſicque electum ipſi Reverendiſſimo in eadem Domo Capitulari prox' inſequente Seſſione debita ſolennitate prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentent<note n="14" place="bottom">The Regiſters of the Upper Houſe do prove, that when the Lower Clergy had in their Place of withdrawing elected a Prolocutor, they then came back to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop and Biſhops, and related the Names of the Perſons they had choſe for the <hi>Prolocutor</hi> and the <hi>Preſenter</hi> of him, and had his Grace's Approbation before his Proroguing in their Preſence to a day, in which the ſaid Prolocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor ſhould be formally preſented. But of late, the Parliament Opening the ſame day with the Convocation has called away their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> before a Report could be made of <hi>ſuch Election,</hi>
                  </note>. His dictis deſcendunt Omnes in Inferiorem Domum ad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum praedictum.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152633:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>FORMA</hi> Eligendi &amp; Praeſentandi <hi>PROLOCUTOREM.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOlet obſervari, ut poſtquam ingreſſi fuerint Inferiorem Domum, in ſedibus ſe decenter collocent<note n="1" place="bottom">Taking <hi>Seats,</hi> and <hi>Sitting</hi> is the firſt Privilege of the Lower Clergy in their ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Room from the Biſhops. For the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> of <hi>England</hi> as not at firſt admitted into the Provincial Council of the Metropolitan and his Suffragans; ſo when upon Secular Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts They were by degrees admitted to be a Part of that <hi>Council,</hi> they ſtill rather waited as <hi>Aſſiſtants,</hi> and never join'd as Co-Aſſeſſors. So as when their Advice or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent was ask'd in a Matter, that requir'd longer conſideration than could be taken on the Spot, <hi>then</hi> it was an Eaſe and Relief to them to withdraw to ſome diſtinct Adjacent Place, where they might with greater Reſt and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom debate and determine of the Subject re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to them.</note>, &amp; ſi Aliqui ex Iis ſint Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarii ſive Sacellani Regiae Majeſtatis, ut hi ſuperiores ſedes occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; atque ut <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus ex Iis propter Dignitatem &amp; Reverentiam, ſeu in eorum abſentia, Decanus<note n="2" place="bottom">The Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, if the King's Chaplain, has a Right to Preſide within his own Church over his Brethren the Clergy Aſſembled by the Archbiſhop's Leave, in order to chuſe a Prolocutor.</note> Eccleſiae Cath' <hi>D.</hi> Pauli London' ſive Archidiaconus London' Praeſidentis<note n="3" place="bottom">The name of <hi>Preſident</hi> was at large ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to any Perſon who <hi>Preſided</hi> or <hi>Moderated</hi> or took the <hi>Chair</hi> in any Eccleſiaſtic or Scholaſtic Meeting. And therefore it is an Affected Error in the Author of <hi>the Power of the L. H. to Adjourn,</hi> &amp;c. to ſay, that whenever the <hi>Word is employ'd in Convocations, it conſtantly ſignifies One that Preſides</hi> in the ſtead of, <hi>and by an authority</hi> derived from <hi>ſome other.</hi> p. 18. c. 1. It is hard to make this definition of a <hi>Preſident</hi> agree with this title here given to the Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s. And 'tis more Abſurd in that Author to affirm, That the <hi>title</hi> of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident as apply'd to the Archbiſhop, is wholly New— and implies a diminution of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> For the Archbiſhop at the Head of his Province could have no greater title than that of his ordinary ſtile <hi>Reverendiſſimus,</hi> appropri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ated to the Archbiſhop, and not capable o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> being aſſum'd by any other Perſon. Yet He was well known to <hi>Preſide</hi> over the whole Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, and is frequently ſaid <hi>Praeeſſe</hi> and <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidere,</hi> from whence He might well have the Name as He had the Office of <hi>Praeſes</hi> and <hi>Praeſidens.</hi> But becauſe the Archbiſhop had power to aſſign this Office to a Deputy or Repreſentative commiſſion'd by Him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any One of his Suffragans ſo delegated, had the Name along with the Dignity of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding,</hi> and is often ſaid <hi>loco Reverendiſſimi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidere.</hi> And again, becauſe in the vacancy of the See of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Dean and Chapter commit the Care of <hi>Preſiding</hi> to the Dean of the Province, the Biſhop of <hi>London;</hi> therefore his Lordſhip is then properly the <hi>Preſident</hi> of Convocation. Not that He <hi>preſides in ſtead of</hi> the Dean and Chapter, for they have no ſuch Power of <hi>Preſiding.</hi> But obſerve, when the title of <hi>Preſident</hi> is ſo aſcrib'd to his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce's <hi>Delegate,</hi> or <hi>Sede vacante</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> it is ſtill a borrowed title, and deriv'd from the Archbiſhop's original Power of <hi>Preſiding,</hi> and imputed to <hi>Them</hi> only, as they <hi>pro hac vice</hi> fill the Place of the ſtanding <hi>Preſident</hi> of the Convocation of a Province, the Metropolitan.</note> officio in hujuſmodi Electione fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatur. Atque ut ad hoc rite procedatur, primum jubebit nomina om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152633:4"/>citatorum &amp; qui tunc intereſſe tenentur à Clerico dictae Inferioris Domus recitari &amp; praeconizari<note n="4" place="bottom">This Preconization or calling over the Names of the Clergy <hi>now</hi> by order of the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour <hi>Preſident,</hi> before they are a Houſe; or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards by order of the <hi>Prolocutor,</hi> when they do become a proper Houſe; is not by any inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Power in <hi>either</hi> Perſon or Aſſembly: but 'tis done by the Authority and for the Service of the Archbiſhop; to Whom the Names of the Abſents ſhould be given; He Alone having the power to judge of the reaſonable Cauſe of their <hi>Abſenting,</hi> and Canonically to puniſh Such as He finds to be contumacious <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters.</hi>
                  </note>. Notatiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Abſentibus, alloquatur prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes atque eorum ſententiam de idoneo Procuratore eligendo ſciſcitetur. Et poſtquam de eo convenerint (quod ſemper quaſi ſtatim<note n="5" place="bottom">The choice of a Prolocutor uſed to be thus diſpatch'd with Eaſe and Expedition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Clergy had <hi>this</hi> only to conſider, what Perſon among 'em would anſwer the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter recommended by the Archbiſhop, <hi>De viro Docto Pio &amp; Fideli:</hi> Agreeing alway on ſuch a One as ſtood right in the Opinion of their Superiours; and ſo was the more Able to keep up the fair Correſpondence and happy Union between the Archbiſhop and Biſhops and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. Upon the firſt Eſtabliſhment of a Prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor, they continually choſe the Archbiſhop's Official or other Miniſter, in Reſpect to their Metropolitan, and in hopes of having their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs negotiated with more Succeſs. In later times when his Grace's Official was not a ſtanding Member, they generally choſe the D. of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, or whoever elſe was Preſident at the Time of Electing. The firſt Diviſions that are known to have hapned about the choice of a Prolocutor, were in 1689. when the Majority were for a Perſon to ſerve a particular Deſign of <hi>Not Acting,</hi> and indeed of <hi>Not Sitting,</hi> which they confeſs to have been <hi>rather their Deſire.</hi>
                  </note> &amp; abſque ullo negotio perfici ſolebat) mox conveniunt inter ſe de Duobus eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioris Ordinis, qui dictum Electum Reverendiſſimo Domino <hi>Cantuar'</hi> in Die ſtatuto debita cum Reverentia &amp; Solennitate praeſentent.</p>
               <p>Quorum Alter ſicut, cum dies advenerit, ipſum Prolocutorem cum La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina &amp; docta Oratione praeſentare tenetur, ſic etiam idem Praeſentatus habitu Doctoratûs indutus conſimilem Orationem ad dictum Reverendiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum Patrem ac Praelatos &amp; caeteros Praeſentes habere debet. Quibus finitis, praefatus Reverendiſſimus Oratione Latina tam Electores quam Praeſentato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem &amp; Preſentatum pro ſua gratia collaudare, ac demum ipſam Electionem ſua
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152633:5"/>Archiepiſcopali Authoritate<note n="6" place="bottom">The Archbiſhop had reſerv'd to himſelf, the expreſs Authority of Approving and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the Choice of a Prolocutor. And if he never once rejected the Perſon preſented to him, it proves, that the Clergy of this Province were alway ſo Wiſe and Happy, as to Agree in One very Acceptable to the Archbiſhop and Biſhops.</note> expreſſe confirmare &amp; approbare non dedigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur. Et ſtatim idem Reverendiſſimus Anglice (ſi placeat) exponere ſolet ulterius bene placitum ſuum<note n="7" place="bottom">Theſe <hi>Gravamina</hi> and <hi>Reformanda</hi> to be conſulted of by the Lower Clergy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the Archbiſhop, were ſuch chiefly as concern'd their Civil Rights. Such <hi>Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances</hi> relating to their Properties and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which they had been uſed to complain of, to the King, and to Petition him for Redreſs when he requir'd their Subſidies and Taxes. And like the Temporal Commons, they often inſiſted upon ſuch Redreſs of Grievances, as a Condition of granting their Aid and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence. This by degrees taught the Clergy in Convocation a like Method of repreſenting to the Archbiſhop and Biſhops, any ſort of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Oppreſſions they lay under from Inferiour Courts and Officers. But then, whatever theſe Grievances were, they were never once caſt into <hi>Reſolutions,</hi> or <hi>Poſitions</hi> of Cenſure and Remonſtrance; but were alway delivered in Articles of Requeſt and Petition or Addreſs, in a decent humble manner. The drawing up of Grievances in a Declaratory Stile, with a ſort of Judicial Condemnation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>em, was a new and peculiar Liberty of the laſt Convocation, when they alſo limited their Complaints, and made 'em againſt the Biſhops only, and their Eccleſiaſtical Government: Never once thinking how to repreſent the Hardſhip of Poor Vicars in bearing an unequal Burden of Taxes; nor the want of a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd Number of Clergy-Commiſſioners to preſerve their Brethren from being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd in Aſſeſſments. Nor to recommend any other Relief or Favour, which upon ſuitable Application to his Grace and their Lordſhips, might poſſibly have been obtain'd from the Legiſlative Power.</note>; Hortando Clerum, ut de rebus communibus quae Reformatione indigent, conſultent &amp; referant die<note n="8" place="bottom">This Paſſage was applied by Dr. <hi>K.</hi> to prove the <hi>Continuance and Intermiſſion of Sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings in the Lower Houſe, as depending interme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately on the Metropolitan, and finally on the Prince.</hi> Occaſ. Letter p. 54. but the Author of P. L. H. applies it to a Meaning directly oppoſite, and makes it an expreſs Argument, that the <hi>Conſultations of the Lower Houſe</hi> were <hi>to be held on Intermediate days as they ſaw beſt; But the Report of 'em was to be made above, on the day appointed for the common Sitting of Both Houſes.</hi> p. 12. c. 2. So the <hi>Narrative</hi> in the <hi>Appendix</hi> p. xiii. would have theſe Words ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being <hi>fairly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtood of the free Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of ſo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſing the Intervals of Seſſions, i. e.</hi> of holding intermediate Seſſions, <hi>ſo as die Statuto (the next Seſſion) muſt be joined with Referant, and the Conſultent be left at large.</hi> But there is <hi>Force</hi> as well as <hi>Art</hi> in detorting theſe Words to apply 'em to the New Pretences of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Seſſions. The Author of P. L. H. is firſt driven upon dividing <hi>conſultent &amp; referant</hi> that he may make the <hi>die Statuto</hi> refer to the latter only; and therefore he puts a ſtop after <hi>Conſultent,</hi> which is not in the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, nor in the two Copies Printed (before the thoughts of ſuch a turn) by Dr. <hi>Atterbury</hi> himſelf in the two ſeveral Editions of his <hi>Rights, Powers,</hi> &amp;c. Nay, it is not in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation at large that is made for the like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in the <hi>Appendix</hi> to the <hi>Narrative.</hi> But in all the Books and Papers I have yet ſeen (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting that P. L. H.) the words are joyn'd as the Conjunction requires, <hi>Conſultent &amp; refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant die ſtatuto.</hi> So as their <hi>Conſulting</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating</hi> may well belong to the <hi>ſame Appointed Day,</hi> which in the ſenſe of thoſe Writers, is the next Seſſion to which the Archbiſhop Continues and Prorogues 'em. Without breaking the words by that feigned ſtop, 'tis ſo hard to divide the application of 'em; that the Writer of the <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix</hi> to the <hi>Narrative</hi> is free to own, we may ſo fairly preſume, <hi>if not by common ſenſe, yet by what we have ſeen;</hi> i. e. by far fetch'd Alluſions to the Parliament. Certainly if this <hi>Form</hi> had meant to provide for any ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Practiſe, it would have ſaid, <hi>De rebus communibus quae Reformatione indigent</hi> ſuo tempore <hi>conſultent; ac denuo Referant die ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuto.</hi> And yet after all, granting the Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation muſt have intervening Days, before the final Day of Report: Might not the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop direct 'em, or allow 'em to let a Part or Committee of 'em meet, and adviſe in the mean while, that they might be ready for a Report againſt the regular Day of Seſſion. This is a Method frequent in the Regiſters, where the Archbiſhop commits Buſineſs to a Select Company, in order to adjuſt and offer it in ſome appointed Seſſion. But in all our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords we meet not with one ſingle Inſtance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 1701, where the Lower Houſe after the Prorogation by the Archbiſhop, formally Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ themſelves to an Intermediate day; and call that Meeting a Seſſion, and there conſult Buſineſs of their own chuſing, independently from the Biſhops. In truth, there never was any proper Synodical Buſineſs of common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to the Church or Religion, that was ever treated of in a Committee of the Lower Houſe <hi>Alone.</hi> But all ſuch Buſineſs was conſtantly referr'd to a joint Committee of Biſhops and Clergy, and by them <hi>together</hi> form'd into a Report to be made to the Archbiſhop and his Suffragans.</note> ſtatuto. Ac ad hunc
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152633:5"/>modum de Seſſione in Seſſionem continuabitur<note n="9" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ad hunc modum</hi> muſt relate to the words immediately foregoing <hi>Die ſtatuto,</hi> which the Author of P. L. H. allows to be <hi>the Day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the common Sitting of Both Houſes.</hi> And the <hi>Appendix</hi> to the <hi>Narrative,</hi> juſtly calls it, <hi>The next Seſſion.</hi> Thus, or after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by the Archbiſhop's Appointment from <hi>one</hi> Seſſion of both Houſes to <hi>another,</hi> the whole Convocation ſhall be continued, as ſhall ſeem expedient to the Archbiſhop upon Counſel of his Brethren, and till the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhall interpoſe by Writ for the Prorogation or the Diſſolution of it.</note> Convocatio quamdiu expedire videbitur, ac donec de eadem diſſolvenda<note n="10" place="bottom">Not a Writ that actually diſſolves, but a Writ for <hi>diſſolving</hi> preſented to the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, who in obedience makes the <hi>Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> The Author of the P. L. H. having aſcrib'd the Power of Aſſembling <hi>only</hi> and <hi>purely</hi> to the King's Writ, does then artfully infer, That <hi>the powers of Proroguing and Diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving are in Law and Reaſon the natural and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Reſult of the former,</hi> p. 3. c. 1. But the Suppoſition indeed is abſolutely falſe. For our Reformed Princes did no more aſſemble the Clergy <hi>only</hi> and <hi>purely</hi> by their own Writ, than their <hi>Popiſh.</hi> Predeceſſors did, when <hi>they</hi> alſo ſent the ſame Writ of Precept to the Archbiſhop, who thereupon did Convene the Clergy <hi>then,</hi> by the ſame Mandate as <hi>now.</hi> In truth as before the Reformation, the Archbiſhops Prorogued and Diſſolved by their own power (as Dr. <hi>A.</hi> confeſſes) even when they aſſembled a Convocation at the King's Command: So the Act of Submiſſion did not at all alter the Conſtitution of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Aſſemblies; only as it reſtrained the Archbiſhop from convening, without having Licenſe and Authority for ſo doing by the King's Writ; which Writ was to be now <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> as it had <hi>Frequently</hi> before been, Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his own Mandate. But neither Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation nor Diſſolution were directly or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately affected by the Statute. Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> did all along actually <hi>Prorogue,</hi> and if he had ſeen a Neceſſity, he might <hi>yet</hi> have legally diſmiſt his Provincial Aſſembly. But indeed King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. to keep a Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Popiſhly affected Clergy more in Awe of a Reforming Parliament, began (even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Act of Submiſſion, and therefore not by Vertue of it) to ſend his Precepts to the Archbiſhop, to Prorogue and Diſſolve the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation at the ſame Times with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; becauſe he could beſt truſt them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch an Awe and Reſtraint. King <hi>Edw.</hi> VI. and Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> were put upon the ſame prudential Methods: While the Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Convocation were ſuſpected as Averſe to the Meaſures taken in Parliament. This Reaſon Alone began and confirmed the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of Royal Writs to command the Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing and Diſſolving a Convocation concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent with every Parliament. Yet the Cuſtom did not bar the legal Prerogative in 1640. Nor is there Any Law but a like Cuſtom, that can now reſtrain the Crown from Iſſuing or not Iſſuing the like Writs at Pleaſure. But obſerve, whenever theſe Writs are Iſſu'd, the Writ it ſelf does not of it ſelf <hi>Prorogue</hi> or <hi>Diſſolve</hi> (as the firſt Writ did not of it ſelf <hi>Convene</hi>) but only declares an Expedience and a Reſolution upon it; and then commands the Archbiſhop to exert his Authority, who in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of ſuch Precept, do's by Himſelf or his Commiſſary Prorogue or Diſſolve the Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by a Schedule of their own <hi>diſtinct</hi> from the Writ; as it was before aſſembled by a <hi>diſtinct</hi> Mandate in obedience to the King's Writ.</note> Breve Regium eidem Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimo praeſentetur.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152633:6"/>
               <p>Et ſciendum eſt quod quotieſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Prolocutor ad praeſentiam Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimi cauſa Convocationis ac tempore Seſſionis<note n="11" place="bottom">By this it appears, that the Prolocutor is never ſuppos'd to be at the Head of the Lower Clergy in any intermediate Seſſion, but only <hi>tempore Seſſionis,</hi> i. e. when both Houſes hold a concurrent Seſſion, and are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for a mutual Intercourſe.</note> acceſſerit, utatur habitu praedicto, ac Janitor ſive virgifer dictae inferioris Domus ipſum reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter antecedat.</p>
               <p>Ejuſdem Prolocutoris est etiam monere omnes ne diſcedant à Civitate <hi>London'</hi> abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> licentia<note n="12" place="bottom">It is here declar'd to be an expreſs Duty of the Prolocutor to Admoniſh All the Members not to go out of Town without Leave of the Archbiſhop. And in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes of former Convocations, there is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Entry of ſuch Solemn Admonition. So as when Occaſions requir'd any Member to retire into the Country, a proper Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Leave was made to the Preſident, and to Him only. Till in this laſt Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, among other ways of attempting to come up to the Appearance of a Houſe of Commons; They fell upon this of asking <hi>Leave of the Houſe</hi> for this or that Member to go into the Country; and this too ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in an Intermediate Seſſion. As in their Minutes of <hi>May</hi> 14. <hi>Memorand. Mr. Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon</hi> Hutton <hi>deſired Leave to go into the Country to hold his Viſitation.</hi> And ſeveral Others of the Majority Side went ſo away without Leave or Knowledge of his Grace, in contempt and open breach of our Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Conſtitution. But upon ſecond thoughts, their own <hi>Narrative</hi> condemns the Practice, and the Men that were guilty of it; by <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying not that his Grace has a Power of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the Attendance of our Members:</hi> and <hi>if the Lower Houſe do give a Leave of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, yet the Member is not perfectly at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty without Leave from the Archbiſhop.</hi> Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. <hi>p.</hi> 49.</note> Reverendiſſimi. Quodque ſtatutis diebus<note n="13" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Statutis diebus</hi> do's alway ſignify the common Days appointed by the Preſident for holding a concurrent Seſſion of Both Houſes. And no notice being ever given of <hi>any other</hi> Days, 'tis a ſure Sign the Lower Clergy ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pretended to make intermediate Seſſions of their own Appointment. The Prolocutor <hi>admoniſhing</hi> 'em to <hi>come early</hi> on theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Convocation Days, was to have 'em in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to attend at the opening of the Seſſion, when the Preſident often took occaſion to inſtruct 'em and adviſe 'em in the Buſineſs of the Day.</note> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtive veniant ad Convocationem. Quodque ſalaria Clericorum<note n="14" place="bottom">The obligation of the Lower Clergy to pay the Salary of the Clerk of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper</hi> as well as of the <hi>Lower</hi> Houſe, is a clear Argument that they are not exempted from that Upper-Houſe: But that indeed the whole <hi>Body</hi> of the Convocation under the <hi>Head</hi> of the Province requires every <hi>Member</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the common Occaſions of being mutually ſerv'd and aſſiſted. And therefore by the Conſtitution of our Provincial Synods there is but <hi>one</hi> Regiſter of Convocation, and <hi>one</hi> Regiſtry of Acts and Minutes: <hi>i. e.</hi> the Regiſter of the Archbiſhop, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtry of his Metropolitan See. His Grace's Principal Regiſter has commonly his Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate or Deputed Officer, and he or his Deputy by virtue of ſuch Office is the ſtanding Regiſter of the whole Convocation. He being able to attend in <hi>Perſon</hi> only on the Upper Houſe, deputes his <hi>Proxy</hi> or Aſſiſtant to attend upon the Lower Houſe; as an Actuary or Scribe to form their Minutes, and prepare their written Correſpondence with the Archbiſhop and Biſhops: Which Actuary or Under-Clerk was never choſe or rejected by the Houſe or the Prolocutor, but was aſſign'd and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs'd by the Superiour Clerk or Regiſter of Convocation. But in the late Aſſembly they were breaking theſe fix'd Rules of Property and Conſtitution, and pretended that the Clerk of the Upper Houſe is but a <hi>Fellow Actuary</hi> with the Clerk of the Lower, who is <hi>choſe</hi> and <hi>imploy'd by the Prolocutor,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contrary to all Right and Fact. <hi>Narrat.</hi> p. 33. 36.
<p>All true Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> will be content with a Convocation to be Held, <hi>Prout ab Antiquo obſervari conſuevit.</hi> And 'tis for that Reaſon, I have here publiſh'd the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire <hi>Form</hi> of Holding a <hi>Reformed Convocation</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant Provincial Synod,</hi> drawn up by an excellent Antiquary Archbiſhop <hi>Parker,</hi> under the Government of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which a ſtrict Regard to the Conſtitution of the Church and State, for a ſtanding Rule to Poſterity, as long as God ſhould bleſs this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Purity of Religion <hi>then</hi> Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd.</p>
                     <p>And the Reading over this <hi>Form Alone,</hi> will abundantly diſcover and refute thoſe late Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters who have labour'd for <hi>Change</hi> and <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> in theſe Matters. There is ſcarce any one of their <hi>Pretences,</hi> but what is really op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Orders and Opinions <hi>here</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd. As you find particularly,
<list>
                           <item>1. Dr. <hi>Atterbury</hi> would have the Conſtitution of <hi>Engliſh Synods</hi> entirely alter'd by the <hi>Act of Submiſſion</hi> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap>; when this <hi>Form</hi> refers All to Ancient Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and to antecedent Cuſtom; without hinting at any one material Change occaſion'd by the <hi>Reformation.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. It is a Pretence of Dr. <hi>A.</hi> that the Parliament Writ is entred in the Front of the Acts of every Synod; and that even by the Provincial Writ the Biſhops and Clergy are ſummon'd directly by the King, not at all by the authority of the Archbiſhop: Whereas <hi>here</hi> is nothing at all of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Writ; nor indeed of the King's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Writ as a Royal Summons; but the <hi>Archiepiſcopal Mandate</hi> only is mention'd, and All Members are expreſly ſaid to be <hi>cited by Authority of the Archbiſhop.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. It is a Notion of the like Author of P. L. H. that the <hi>Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates</hi> or Returns which the Dean and Suffragans make to the Metropolitan are <hi>in Virtue of the King's Writ,</hi> and not at all in Virtue of the Archbiſhop's Mandate; whereas here the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> brings in the <hi>Mandate</hi> only, and Certifies nothing but the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>that</hi> ſingle Mandate.</item>
                           <item>4. He has ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd a new Claim to the Lower Houſe to give leave of Abſence to their Members, without Application to the Archbiſhop; when <hi>here</hi> the Members appear before the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop only, and the Penalty of their Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is reſerv'd to <hi>Him alone;</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locutor is to admoniſh all the Lower Clergy of this Duty, that they do not preſume to go out of Town without the Archbiſhop's Leave.</item>
                           <item>5. Another Practice was begun of the Lower Clergy chuſing their own Buſineſs, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Reſolutions,</hi> in very important Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, without any conſult with, or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Archbiſhop and Biſhops; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>here</hi> the Archbiſhop is firſt to declare the Cauſe of his coming, and the Reaſons of open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Convocation; and then the Inferiour Clergy proceed upon Inſtructions, and in mutual Concert with the Upper-Houſe in joint Committees.</item>
                           <item>6. The Prolocutor has been made Head Governour and Preſident of the Lower-Houſe; but the Archbiſhop not a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of Convocation: When <hi>here</hi> a Prolocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor is elected and confirm'd by Authority of the Archbiſhop, and is to attend his Grace <hi>when</hi> and <hi>where</hi> he ſhall be Bidden or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: And when by the very Act of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity 14. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. the two Archbiſhops are more than once call'd the <hi>Preſidents of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations</hi> within their reſpective Provinces.</item>
                           <item>6. They took up a ſingularity of intermediate Seſſions: When <hi>here</hi> is no intimation of any Meeting but in <hi>Die Statuto,</hi> which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves acknowledge to be the next Seſſion ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Archbiſhop for the joint Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of both Houſes. And ſo in many other Particulars, they have advanc'd Notions and Claims either directly Oppoſite, or at leaſt not at all agreeing, to this GOOD OLD FORM.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </note> tam Superioris quam Inferioris Domus, &amp; Janitoris inferioris Domus juxta antiquam taxationem, quatenus eorum quemlibet concernit, fideliter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvant.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152633:6"/>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152633:7"/>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>State ſuper vias Antiquas.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152633:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
